Soviet Union Jewish Subject Files, Inclusive: 1952-2002, undated, Bulk: 1971-1992, undated
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
Soviet Union Jewish Subject Files
Inclusive: 1952-2002, undated, Bulk: 1971-1992, undated
Baylor University, The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society http://www.baylor.edu/kestoncenter/
30
The Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society
19 A4 document boxes
The Soviet Union Jewish Subject Files contain a variety of materials on persecution of and discrimination against Jews in the Soviet Union and post-Soviet Russia.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Keston College, originally founded in 1969 as the Center for the Study of Religion and Communism with the named changed to Keston College in 1974, collected and publicized details about religious persecution behind the Iron Curtain, becoming “the voice of the voiceless.” After the collapse of communism in the 1990s, Keston College moved to Oxford and downsized due to decreased funding. The name eventually changed to Keston Institute. In 2007, the Institute transferred the Keston Archive and Library to the newly created Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society at Baylor University.
Keston collected, verified, translated, and disseminated information received from believers in the Soviet Union, Poland, Romania, Czechoslovakia, Hungary, Yugoslavia, Bulgaria, and other communist countries. The Keston Archive and Library housed numerous letters, petitions, reports and underground publications (Samizdat) from believers of various denominations along with officially published books and periodicals.
In the late 1960s, Keston began collecting materials on the persecution of Jews in the Soviet Union.
Oppression of Jews in Russia and the USSR has a deep history. The predominately Orthodox population of Imperial Russia viewed Jewish religion as alien and considered Jewish initiative and progressive philosophy harmful to the traditional Russian world. With rare exceptions, authorities did not allow Jews to live in cities in central Russian regions and they could settle only within government designated territories. Therefore, Russian Jews formed large communities in Ukraine, Belorussia, Poland, and Lithuania. Oppressive state policies and popular prejudice and antisemitism resulted in the 1880s pogroms or violent riots.
In 1905, Tsar Nicholas II signed a manifesto on religious tolerance which changed the popular opinion of Jews. The first Choral Synagogue opened in Moscow in 1906. After the fall of the Tsarist regime, the Provisional Government abolished designated territories and relaxed state antisemitic policies. Unfortunately, the 1917 Bolshevik Revolution marked the collapse of such ideals and disappointed Jews who were conscious of their religion, cultural history, and language and anxious to preserve their national identity and tradition.
In the 1920s, authorities arrested, executed, and exiled many Jewish religious leaders in response to their attempt to create a reformed religious organization uniting Jewish communities in the USSR. Instead, the Soviet government attempted to create a state controlled alternative Jewish organization similar to the Orthodox “Living Church.” The attempt failed because of a protest campaign organized by Rabi Yosef Schneersohn, and the Soviet government responded with a wave of persecution. They declared proponents of Jewish consciousness and tradition as supporters of Western aggression. Attacks on old Jewish bourgeoisie and intelligentsia led to their almost complete disappearance. Authorities closed many synagogues and yeshivas and executed or sent to gulags rabbis and other Jewish religious leaders. Stalin’s party purges targeted old Bolsheviks loyal to Lenin who opposed antisemitism and resulted in the growth of antisemitic sentiments among party members. In the 1930s, the Jewish reformed movement almost ceased trying to avoid anti-religious persecution, Jewish believers stopped attending synagogues and distanced themselves from religious life.
During World War II, the Nazis killed a vast majority of Hasidic Jews in Ukraine, Belorussia, and the western Russian territories. The state always included the loss of Jewish lives in general Soviet loses to avoid encouraging national consciousness.
After the war, the Soviet government’s policy toward Jews changed to stop mass emigration. Authorities facilitated creation of Jewish cultural autonomy to control Jewish communities. The Jewish Autonomous District of Birobidzhan was created in 1928 in Khabarovskii Krai, on the border with China. In 1958, speaking of Birobidzhan District, Soviet leader Nikita Khrushchev stated that the attempt to create a mass Jewish settlement was a failure, for which he blamed Soviet Jews, who never liked collective work and group discipline. In 1990, most of the District’s Jewish population emigrated. In 1947, the USSR supported the creation of the state of Israel. However, authorities deprived Soviet Jews the opportunity to contact or visit their historic territory.
In the 1950s, official anti-Jewish measures included the closure of the Jewish Anti-Fascist Committee, arrest and trial of prominent doctors under the Doctors’ Plot, and prosecution of hundreds of Jews for “economic crimes.” Official antisemitism reemerged in the press. Increasing antisemitic sentiment prompted the beginning of a new Jewish national and religious identity movement. The movement developed alongside similar dissident religious movements in other confessions, included Jews who grew up in secular families but were conscious of their Jewish heritage, and led to the beginning of a mass exodus of Jews from the USSR in the 1970s.
The Perestroika period was marked by the rise of chauvinist and nationalist organizations, like Pamyat, which became popular among people supporting Greater Russian nationalism and antisemitism. In the late1980s and early 1990s, members of extremist nationalistic organizations driven by racist and antisemitic sentiments targeted Jews, vandalized their cemeteries, and facilitated pogroms throughout the Soviet. State and republic authorities chose the policy of non-involvement and failed to recognize the criminal activity as race driven.
By the mid-1990s, two competing central Jewish religious organizations formed in Russia: Congress of the Jewish Religious Organizations and Association and Federation of Jewish Communities. All Russian Jewish religious organizations were required to register with at least one of them to comply with the 1997 Russian Federal Law on the Freedom of Consciousness.
Scope and Content
The Soviet Union Jewish Subject Files contain materials on the state oppressive practices and discrimination against Jews in the Soviet Union and Jews’ fight for human rights. The materials cover a period from 1952 to 2002, with the bulk from 1971 to 1992. The most notable topics include but are not limited to Jewish religion and national identity, Russian nationalism and anti-Semitism, relations between the Soviet Union and the state of Israel, mass emigration of Jews from the Soviet Union, international support for refuseniks, and Leningrad airplane hijacking case. Individual accounts of persecution include the cases of Iosif Begun and Anatoly Shcharansky.
Some materials pertain to discrimination against Jews and rise of nationalism and antisemitism in post-Soviet Russia.
The files consist of newspaper clippings, bibliographic references, reports, and various forms of Samizdat, including underground publications and unofficially circulated documents and records.
Arrangement
The Keston Center received most of the Soviet Union Jewish materials in files organized by subject. This original filing system has largely been preserved. Unprocessed materials were organized thematically and chronologically.
The Soviet Union Jewish Subject Files are currently arranged into two series: I. General and II. Samizdat.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to the Keston Center for Religion, Politics, and Society in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 30.
Related Resources
Related references
Bourdeaux, Michael., and S. B. Filatov. Sovremennai︠a︡ religioznai︠a︡ zhizn)' Rossii: opyt sistematicheskogo opisanii︠a︡. (Moskva: “Logos,” 2003).
Kochan, Lionel. The Jews in Soviet Russia Since 1917, 2nd ed. (Oxford University Press, 1972).
Birobidzhan, Russia. Jewish Virtual Library. A Project of Aice. Accessed on 2021 March 12.
Freedman, Robert Owen. Soviet Jewry in the 1980s: the Politics of Anti-Semitism and Emigration and the Dynamics of Resettlement. (Duke University Press, 1989).
Index Terms
Subjects (Persons)
Begun, Yosif, 1932-; Buṭman, Hilel, 1932-; Kuznet︠s︡ov, Ėduard.
Subjects (Organizations)
Russkoe nat︠s︡ional)'noe edinstvo (Organization: Russia)
Places
Israel -- Foreign relations -- Soviet Union.; Israel — Emigration and immigration.; Russia (Federation) -- Ethnic relations.; Russia (Federation) -- Politics and government -- 1991-; Soviet Union -- Emigration and immigration.; Soviet Union -- Foreign relations -- Israel.; Soviet Union -- Politics and Government.
Subjects
Antisemitism — Russia (Federation); Civil rights -- Soviet Union.; Communism and religion -- Soviet Union.; Human rights -- Russia (Federation); Human rights -- Soviet Union.; Jews -- Russia.; Jews -- Soviet Union.; Judaism — Russia — History.; Persecution -- Russia (Federation); Refuseniks -- Soviet Union.; Shcharansky, Anatoly.; Xenophobia — Russia (Federation)
Genres
Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Records (Documents)
- General, 1952-2002, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  The series contains information about oppressive state practices against Jews in the Soviet Union, discrimination against Jewish nationals, and their fight for basic human rights and freedoms.
  The series is in good condition.
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (1 of 18), 1950-1966 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (2 of 18), 1967-1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (3 of 18), 1970 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (4 of 18), 1971 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (5 of 18), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (6 of 18), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (7 of 18), 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (8 of 18), 1975 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (9 of 18), 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (10 of 18), 1978 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (11 of 18), 1980-1983 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (12 of 18), 1984-1986 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (13 of 18), 1987 January-September (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (14 of 18), 1987 October-December (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (15 of 18), 1988 January-June (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (16 of 18), 1988 July-December (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (17 of 18), 1989-1992, 2001 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Jewish Religion. Jews. General (18 of 18), undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Jews in the USSR. History. General (1 of 3), 1952-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Jews in the USSR. History. General (2 of 3), 1979-1989, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jews in the USSR. History. General (3 of 3), 1985 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Jews in the USSR. History. Babii Yar, 1966, 1975-1981, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Jews in the USSR. History. Baltic States, 1971-1987 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Jews in the USSR. History. Ukraine, 1969-1974, 1986-1987 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Jews in Russia. History. Before the Russian Revolution, 1978-1993, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Jews in the USSR. History Soviet Period, 1954, 1959, 1979, 1983-1987, 1993-2001 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. General, 1977, 1983, 1986-1987, 1991, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Abramov, Moshe, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Azbel, David and Vladimir, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Azbel, Mark, 1974-1975, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Begun, Iosif (1 of 2), 1974, 1976-1984 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Begun, Iosif (2 of 2), 1985-1988, undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Berenshtein, Iosif, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Bogomolny, Benjamin, 1984, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Brodsky, Vladimir, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Butman, Hillel, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Davidovich, Yefim, 1975-1976 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Elbert, Lev, 1981-1983 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Elistratov, Batsheva, 1979, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Esas, Ilya, 1981-1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Fain, Benjamin, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Fainberg, Viktor, 1974, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Feigin, Girsh, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Feldman, Alexander, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Flerov, Inessa, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Fradkova, Nadezhda, 1983-1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Fridman, Kim, 1979, 1981-1982 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Geiskes, Grigori, 1980, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Gluzman, Semyon, 1974-1981 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Goldshtein Isai and Grigori, 1973, 1979-1986 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Gorodetsky, Yakov, 1983, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Gulko, Boris, 1982, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Brailovsky, Viktor and Irina, 1974-1984 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Ioffe, Alexander, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Kelbert, Leonid, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Kerbel, Adel and Mikhail, 1972-1974 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Kislik, Vladimir, 1977-1982 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Khantis, Yankel, 1972 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Khasin (Khassin), Gennadi, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Kochubievsky, Felix, 1968-1971, 1980-1983 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Kremen, Mikhail, 1982-1983 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Krylsky, Yan, 1972, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Kukui, Valeri, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Kushnir, Alexander, 1982-1983, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Lein, Evgeny, 1981, 1983-1984, undated (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Lerner, Alexander, 1971-1983 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Levich, Benjamin and Family, 1972-1978 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Liubarsky, Lazar, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Leviev, Mikhail, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Lurie Family, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Makarenko, Mikhail, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Malkin, Anatoly, 1975, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Markish, David, 1971-1973 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Neiman, Naum, 1980, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Mendeleevich, Iosif, 1978-1981 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Mesh, Yakov, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Mirkind, Anatoly, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Mashpits, Mark, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Nudel, Ida, 1974-1988 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Palatnik, Raisa, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Panov, Valery, Panova, Galina, 1972-1980 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Paritsky, Alexander, 1980-1984 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Perelman, Viktor, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Polsky, Viktor, 1974-1976 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Prussakov, Valentin, 1971-1972 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Rips, Ilya, 1969-1972, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Roitburd, Lev, 1975, 1980 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Rubin, Vitaly, 1972, 1974-1975, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Shcharansky, Anatoly (Sharansky, Natan), 1977-1988, undated (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Shkolnik, Itskhak (Itzhak), 1973 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Shtern, Mikhail, 1974-1977 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Slepak, Vladimir, 1972, 1978-1984, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Smeliansky, Alla, 1979, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Tarnopolsky, Yuri, 1982-1987 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Temkin, Aleksandr, Temkin, Marina, 1972-1973 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Tsukerman, Boris, 1968, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Voronel, Aleksandr, 1974 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Zand, Mikhail, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Zisels, Iosif, 1978-1979 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. Zubko, Stanislav, 1981-1983, 1985 (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Individual Jewish Believers. List of Names, 1975, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. Synagogue Administration, 1976-1982, 1987, 1996 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. Lists of Synagogues, 1972-1985, undated (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. Individual Synagogues, 1966-1988 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. Chief Rabbinate, 1977, 1984-1985, 2001 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. State Policies toward Jews. General, 1965-1966, 1972-1986, 1992-1993 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. State Policies toward Jews. Individual Cases, 1986 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. State Policies toward Jews. Legislation, 1976, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. State Policies toward Jews. Opening and Reopening of Synagogues, 1990, 1998 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. State Policies toward Jews. Registration of Synagogues, 1980, 1984 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. State Policies toward Jews. Commendation in Secular Press, 1979, 1980, 1986 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Jewish Religion in the USSR. State Policies toward Jews. Synagogue Access to Mass Media, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. General (1 of 2), 1962-1972 February (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. General (2 of 2), 1972 Mart-1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Harassment, 1974-1987, undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Physical Assault, 1967, 1971-1988 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Disruption of Meetings. Denial of Rights to Assembly, 1976-1987 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Fines, 1981-1987, undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Interrogations, 1977-1986 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Trials. General (1 of 2), 1971-1979 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Trials. General (2 of 2), 1981-1987, undated (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Trials. Shtern, Mikhail, 1974-1975 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Imprisonment. General (1 of 4), 1967-1979 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Imprisonment. General (2 of 4), 1980-1984 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Imprisonment. General (3 of 4), 1985 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Imprisonment. General (4 of 4), 1986-1987 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. State Interference in Jewish Affairs. Legal Disabilities, 1971-1987, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers Relating to Religious Education, 1984-1986 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. State Interference in Jewish Affairs. Expropriation, Desecration, or Demolition of Religious Buildings, 19771-1988, 1994, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Discrimination in Employment, 1970-1987, undated (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Discrimination in Education, 1977-1988, undated (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Misuse of Psychiatry, 1973-1987 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Attacks in Media, 1964, 1974-1988 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. House Searches, 1976-1986 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Oppressive Practices against Jewish Believers. Loss of Parental Rights, 1977, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Jewish Religious Life, 1975-1989, 1996-1998, 2002, undated (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Jewish Religious Life. Festivals. Anniversaries, 1967-1987, 1991, 1994 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Jewish Religious Life. Services and Rituals. General, 1967, 1976-1988, 1991, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Jewish Religious Life. Services and Rituals. Burial, 1984-1987 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Jewish Religious Life. Services and Rituals. Mikvah, 1984-1988 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Jewish Religious Life. Services and Rituals. Observance of the Law, 1979-1987 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Jewish Religious Life. Holy Places, 1977-1987 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Jewish Religious Community Life, 1977, 1983-1985, 2001 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Jewish Religious Life. Defections from Faith, 1977, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Jewish Religious Life. Official Religious Publications, 1976-1985, 1989 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - Jewish Clergy. General, 1971-1972, 1980, 1983, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - Individual Jewish Clergy. General, 1971-1976, 1984 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - Individual Jewish Clergy. Iakov Fishman, 1972, 1976-1979, 1983 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - Individual Jewish Clergy. Jehuda Levin, 1971-1972 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - Individual Jewish Clergy. Adolf Shevich, 1980-1984, 1987 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Jewish Clergy. Statistics, 1982-1983 (Box 8, Folder 15)